Guide to the David Gascoyne Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Alan Clodd Collection of David Gascoyne, circa 1910-2002; Series IV; 4.59; (12 boxes)
  - Correspondence
    - David Gascoyne Correspondence
      - Incoming
        - Norres, Peter, 1972 July 19 (Box 10, Folder 201)
        - Oxford University Press, 1970 (Box 10, Folder 202)
        - Parris, Harry, 1978 Oct 11 (Box 10, Folder 203)
        - Penguin Books Ltd., 1970, undated (Box 10, Folder 204)
        - Podnieks, Elizabeth, ?1995 Jun (Box 10, Folder 205)
        - Quayle, Eric, 1970 Jun 22 (Box 10, Folder 206)
        - Quinn, Sister Bernetta, 1975 Jul 22 (Box 10, Folder 207)
        - [Raine], Kathleen, circa 1952-69 (Box 10, Folder 208)
        - Rainier, Priaulx, 1956, 1976-78 (Box 10, Folder 209)
        - Ray, Paul C., 1970 Apr 2 (Box 10, Folder 210)
        - [Reverchou-Jouve], Blanche, undated (Box 10, Folder 211)
        - Royal Court of Justice, official solicitor, 1969-71 (Box 10, Folder 212)
        - Rudolph, Anthony, 1979 (Box 10, Folder 213)
        - Sherrard, Philip, 1972 Jun 29 (Box 10, Folder 214)
        - Style, O-lan, 1978 Apr 23 (Box 10, Folder 215)
        - Taylor, Hasel, 1970 Jan 24 (Box 10, Folder 216)
        - Temple, F., undated (Box 10, Folder 217)
        - Thorp, Michael, 1993 Jan 12 (Box 10, Folder 218)
        - Thorpe, Leslie, 1954 Jan 25 (Box 10, Folder 219)
        - Verzola, Ruggero, 1954 Feb 3 (Box 10, Folder 220)
        - Young, Wayland, 1956 May 5 (Box 10, Folder 221)
        - _____, Elizabeth, undated (Box 10, Folder 222)
        - _____, Lesley and H. ____, undated (Box 10, Folder 223)
        - _____, Mary, undated (Box 10, Folder 224)
        - _____, Michael, 1956 (Box 10, Folder 225)
        - _____, Sydney, 1978 Apr 19 (Box 10, Folder 226)
        - _____, Sylvia, undated (Box 10, Folder 227)
        - Illegible (2 letters), undated (Box 10, Folder 228)
        - Unsigned (1 letter), undated (Box 10, Folder 229)
          An account of a visit to East Berlin, 67 pages, manuscript
      - Outgoing
        All are holograph drafts, unless otherwise noted.
        - Agenda, letters to the editor, 1982 (Box 11, Folder 230)
        - Anders, Richard, 1982 Jul (Box 11, Folder 231)
        - Auster, Paul, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 232)
        - Baker, Mark, 1982 Aug 11 (Box 11, Folder 233)
        - Bamford, Christopher, 1982 Aug (Box 11, Folder 234)
        - Caraiou, Jon, 1983 Feb 19 (Box 11, Folder 235)
        - Davenport, John, 1954 (Box 11, Folder 236)
        - Dickens, Anthony, 1939-40 (Box 11, Folder 237)
        - Ellis, Anthony, typed copy, 1988 Dec 13 (Box 11, Folder 238)
        - Gascoyne, Leslie and Winfred, postcards, 1954-69 (Box 11, Folder 239-245)
        - Gent, Robert, copy, corrected, 1988 Sep 26 (Box 11, Folder 246)
        - The Independent, letter to the Editor, copy, corrected, 1990 Feb 4 (Box 11, Folder 247)
        - Jenkins, Alan, 1988 (Box 11, Folder 248)
        - Lounchbury, Michael, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 249)
        - Mondello, Franco, 1982 Jul 8 (Box 11, Folder 250)
        - Oxford University Press, 1987 (Box 11, Folder 251)
        - Paci, Francesca Romana, 1982 May 27 (Box 11, Folder 252)
        - Raine, Kathleen, 1950, undated (Box 11, Folder 253)
        - Stanford, Derek, 1979-81 (Box 11, Folder 254)
        - [Smart,] Elizabeth, undated (Box 11, Folder 255)
        - Times Literary Supplement, letter to the Editor, 1981 Sep 22 (Box 11, Folder 256)
        - Tristan, Frederick, 1982 Aug 25 (Box 11, Folder 257)
        - _____, Claude, [circa 1950s] (Box 11, Folder 258)
  - Writings
    Notebooks are arranged chronologically. General writings are arranged alphabetically by title of work except for translations of the work of Pierre Jean Jouve, which are filed under Jouve.
    - Notebooks
      - "The Pearl in the Pigsty", [circa 1940s] (Box 12, Folder 259)
      - "Notes for Poems", 1948-49 (Box 12, Folder 260)
      - Drafts of poems, loose sheets, holograph, [circa 1954] (Box 12, Folder 261)
      - Notebook, [circa 1954] (Box 12, Folder 262)
        Includes: notes on Jouve translations
        Accompanied by 2 photographs of Winfred Gascoyne and unidentified woman
      - "Food Notes, etc.", 1958-69 (Box 12, Folder 263)
        Includes: notes on The Sun at Midnight.
      - Notebook, 1979 (Box 12, Folder 264)
        Includes: draft of a preface to Roberto Sanesi's translation of the Collected Poems of T.S. Eliot
      - "Rough drafts of texts (prose)", 1984 (Box 12, Folder 265)
      - Notebook, 1984 (Box 12, Folder 266)
      - "Drafts of letters, articles, notes, etc.", 1985 (Box 12, Folder 267)
      - Notebook, 1985 (Box 12, Folder 268)
        Includes: account of the 1st Nordic Poetry Festival, Reykjavik
      - "Miscellaneous", 1985 (Box 12, Folder 269)
      - Notebook, 1991 (Box 12, Folder 270)
        Includes: review of Surrealist Games
      - "Rough Drafts", 1991-92 (Box 12, Folder 271)
      - Notebook, 1992 (Box 12, Folder 272)
      - Notes, holograph loose sheets, 1950s-1980s (Box 12, Folder 273)
        Includes: "Novalis" and "My 1st Nocturnal Prayer"
    - General Writings
      - "Benjamin Péret: An Introduction," typescript, corrected, undated (Box 12, Folder 274)
      - "The book of the North-Western desire for a South-Western resting-place," poem, typescript, undated (Box 12, Folder 275-276)
      - Collected Verse Translations
        - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 13, Folder 277-279)
        - Correspondence, 1966-70 (Box 13, Folder 280)
      - "Contrasting triumphs," review of Extending the Territory by Elizabeth Jennings and The Immolation of Aleph by John Heath-Stubbs, notes and typescript, corrected, after 1978 (Box 13, Folder 281)
      - "David Gascoyne as a translator," poems selected and introduced by Robin Skelton, typescript for a radio broadcast signed by Robin Skelton, 1968 (Box 13, Folder 282)
      - "Elegiac stanzas in memory of Alban Berg," typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 283)
      - Encounter With Silence, with an introduction by Roger Scott, typescript, copy, 1998 (Box 13, Folder 284)
      - The Fire of Vision
        - "George Barker at Seventy," essay, typescript, corrected, 1982 Oct (Box 13, Folder 285)
        - Correspondence, 1995-96 (Box 13, Folder 286)
      - "From what or whom do womenizers flee?", poem, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 13, Folder 287)
      - Journal 1936-37
        - Typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 288-289)
        - Proof, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 290-291)
      - Jouve, Pierre Jean, translations of
        - "Evening prayer," typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 292)
        - "The present greatness of Mozart," essay, typescript, undated (Box 13, Folder 293)
        - "The Unconscious: Spirituality :: Catastrophe," typescript, copy, undated (Box 13, Folder 294)
        - Various poems, typescripts, corrected, 1939-1940, 1966 (Box 13, Folder 295)
          Accompanied by letter from Douglas Cockerell and Son to H.A. Clodd
      - Lawrence Durrell
        - Proof, 1993 (Box 14, Folder 296)
        - Correspondence, 1992-93 (Box 14, Folder 297)
      - "Marshes of Mazur," poem, typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 298)
        Translated from the Czech by David Gascoyne
      - "The most astonishing book in the English language," essay, typescript, copy, [circa 1992] (Box 14, Folder 299)
      - New English Weekly contributions, copies, 1933-34 (Box 14, Folder 300)
      - New Verse, reviews, copies, 1935-36 (Box 14, Folder 301)
      - Night Thoughts, radio broadcast, typescript, 1955 (Box 14, Folder 302)
      - "OAHSPE," essay, typescript, copy, undated (Box 14, Folder 303)
      - "Ontological Freedom of Choice," short prose
        - Typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 304)
        - Typescript, copy, undated (Box 14, Folder 305)
          Accompanied by a note from Roger Scott
      - Paris Journal 1937-39
        - Partial typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 306)
        - Typescript, corrected, undated (Box 14, Folder 307-308)
        - Notes on corrections, printing and publication, 1977-89 (Box 14, Folder 309)
        - Proof, undated (Box 14, Folder 310)
        - Correspondence, 1974-78 (Box 14, Folder 311)
      - "Postface to Journals," holograph, 1989 (Box 14, Folder 312)
      - "A Quiet Mind," short story, typescript, copy, undated (Box 14, Folder 313)
      - Review of Naissance d'une passion and Fantôme d'une puce by Michel Braudeau, typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 314)
      - "A Rondel for the Fourth Decade," poem, typescript, undated (Box 14, Folder 315)
      - Selected Prose
        - Preface, by Roger Scott, typescript, copy, 1998 (Box 14, Folder 316)
        - Introduction, by Kathleen Raine, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 14, Folder 317)
        - "History of the Womb or Nine Months' Horror," film scenario, typescript, copy, [circa 1997] (Box 14, Folder 318)
        - Typescript, copies, undated (Box 14, Folder 319-321)
      - A Selection of Unpublished Poems & Translations from Notebook, 1950, typescript, [circa 1997] (Box 14, Folder 322)
      - Selected Verse Translations
        - Poems to be included in the collection, typescripts, holographs and copies, some corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 323-235)
        - Typescript, copy, 1996 (Box 15, Folder 326)
        - Gascoyne's translation of Benjamin Fondane's "Rimbaud the Hooligan" in PN Review, No. 12, 1979 (Box 15, Folder 327)
        - Correspondence and notes, 1995-96 (Box 15, Folder 328)
      - "Self-discharged," radio broadcast, typescript, copy, corrected, 1985 (Box 15, Folder 329)
      - The Sun at Midnight
        - Aphorisms, holograph, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 330)
        - Aphorisms, typescript, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 331)
        - Copies of essay published in Two Rivers, 1969 (Box 15, Folder 332)
      - Surrealism Resurveyed, typescript, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 333)
      - Three Poems
        - "Half-an-hour," poem, typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 334)
        - "On rereading Jacob Boehme's 'Aurora'," poem, typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 335)
        - Partial typescript, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 336)
        - Proof, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 337)
        - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 15, Folder 338)
      - "Trois poèmes d'entre les élégies londonniennes," typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 339)
      - Wartime Journal
        - Partial typescript, corrected, undated (Box 15, Folder 340)
        - Correspondence, 1983-85 (Box 15, Folder 341)
      - The Winged Victory, a collection of poems, partial typescript, copy, 1997 (Box 15, Folder 342)
      - Various titles, notes and poems, typescript, undated (Box 15, Folder 343)
      - Untitled poem, typescript, corrected, [circa 1964] (Box 15, Folder 344)
        Begins "Our gentle sister Memory,/Our brother Brute Desire"; accompanied by a note from Alan Clodd
    - Writings of others
      - Gascoyne, Judy, My Love Affair with Life, typescript, 1999 (Box 16, Folder 345)
      - Reed, Jeremy, introduction to Conductors of Chaos, typescript, [circa 1996] (Box 16, Folder 346)
      - Reed, Jeremy, For David Gascoyne's Eightieth Birthday
        - Corrected Proof, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 347)
        - Correspondence, 1996 (Box 16, Folder 348)
      - Reed, Jeremy, review of Selected Poems, typescript, copy, [1995] (Box 16, Folder 349)
      - Scott, Roger, Biography of Roger Roughton (1916-1941), typescript, copy, undated (Box 16, Folder 350)
      - Scott, Roger, Memorium for David Gascoyne, typescript, copy, 2001 (Box 16, Folder 351)
      - [Stanford, Derek], "Salute to David Gascoyne for his Sixty-Fifth Birthday," holograph, [circa 1981] (Box 16, Folder 352)
      - [Romer, Stephen], "Nénuphars, nymphéas," poem dedicated to David Gascoyne, typescript, [1998?] (Box 16, Folder 353)
  - Other papers
    - Memoranda of agreement, 1956, 1968 (Box 16, Folder 354)
    - Baptismal certificate for John Win Gascoyne, 1922 Sep 18 (Box 16, Folder 355)
    - Clippings and reviews related to David Gascoyne, copies, 1979-98 (Box 16, Folder 356)
    - "Blue at the throat," broadside from a performance with Aidan Andrew Dun at Quay Arts, 1998 (Box 16, Folder 357)
  - Artwork
    Artwork is arranged as the Beinecke Library acquired it.
    - "Anarchist Arabesque," drawing, signed, 1952 or 1962 (Box 17, Folder 358)
    - Untitled gouache drawing/découpage, undated (Box 17, Folder 359)
    - "Conches Persanes," drawing, signed, undated (Box 17, Folder 360)
    - "Impacts," drawing, signed, 1963 (Box 17, Folder 361)
    - 6 untitled gouache drawings, signed, 1960-63 (Box 17, Folder 362)
      Accompanied by letter from Mrs. V.L. Davies to Alan Clodd dated 1987 Jun 2
    - Untitled gouache drawing, signed, undated (Box 17, Folder 363)
    - "Soleil de paon ovale," drawing, signed, undated (Box 17, Folder 364)
    - "Frontier," drawing, signed, undated
    - "Blatant Invention," drawing, signed, undated
  - Photographs
    Arranged roughly by subject.
    - David Gascoyne, Radio Times, Hulton Picture Library, includes a negative, 1951 (Box 18, Folder 365)
    - David Gascoyne and Meraud Geuvara at Tour de César, Provence, includes negatives, 1950s (Box 18, Folder 366)
    - Three photographs of David Gascoyne with HEC, 1976-84 (Box 18, Folder 367)
    - Frank Taylor, photographic portrait of David Gascoyne, signed by David Gascoyne, [circa 1990s] (Box 18, Folder 368)
    - Photograph of a drawing of David Gascoyne by Jessica Dismarr in the 1930s, undated (Box 18, Folder 369)
    - Photograph of an exhibition of English surrealists, including a painting by David Gascoyne, 1993 (Box 18, Folder 370)
    - Gascoyne family photographs, 1910s-2000s (Box 18, Folder 371-389)
      Identified subjects include Leslie and Winfred Gascoyne, Tony Gascoyne and family, John Gascoyne and family, Florence Mole, and David Gascoyne (age 2 1/2 to adult)
  - Audio recordings
    Arranged chronologically.
    Existence and Location of Copies
    Reference copies of sound recordings are filed in the folders.
    - "David Gascoyne reads and discusses a selection of his own poems", 1982 (Box 19, Folder 390)
    - Bath Literature Festival, 1997 Feb 23 (Box 19, Folder 391)
    - Procession to private sector, 1998 Jun (Box 19, Folder 392)
    - "David & the Chevalier," British Broadcasting Corporation, undated (Box 19, Folder 393)
    - Night Thoughts, undated (Box 19, Folder 394)
    - Requiem, Gascoyne and Rainier, undated (Box 19, Folder 395)
- Oversize, 4.94; (4 boxes)
  - "The Sun at Midnight" (Series II), [circa 1940s] (Box 20, Folder 396)
  - "Criticism and elicudation of the conception of freedom," holograph draft (Series II), undated (Box 20, Folder 397)
  - "Last Judgement," holograph draft (Series II), ?1946 (Box 20, Folder 398)
  - A Portfolio of New Poems (Series II), 1948 (Box 20, Folder 399)
  - "Works of Novalis," holograph, one sheet (Series II), undated (Box 20, Folder 400)
  - "Works of Novalis," prints and collected artwork (Series II), undated (Box 20, Folder 401-402)
  - "Works of Novalis," prints and collected artwork (Series II), undated (Box 21, Folder 403-407)
  - Document box annotated by Gascoyne (Series III), undated (Box 22)
  - Clippings and ephemera (Series III), [circa 1945-46] (Box 23, Folder 408)
  - "Frontier," signed (Series IV), undated (Box 23, Folder 409)
  - "Blatant Invention," signed (Series IV), undated (Box 23, Folder 410)
- Restricted Fragile, 0.42; (1 box)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 24: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - David Gascoyne reads and discusses a selection of his own poems, 1982; 1; 01:34:38 (Box 24, Item barcode 39002091243833)
  - Bath Literature Festival, 1997 February 23; 1; 00:52:44 (Box 24, Item barcode 39002091243841)
  - Procession to private sector, 1998 June; 1; 00:45:08; The program is distorted at times. High background noise can be heard on the tape. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002091243858)
  - David and the Chevalier, BBC programme, undated; 1; 00:17:05; A high amount of hiss can be heard on the tape. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002091243866)
  - "Night Thoughts", undated; 1; 00:54:05; A high amount of buzz can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. Sound can be heard from the left channel only beginning at about 48:08 until the end of the tape. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002091243874)
  - "Requiem", side A only, Gascoyne / Rainier, undated; 1; 01:18:55; High frequency background noise and static can be heard on the tape. The program is distorted at times. (Box 24, Item barcode 39002091243882)